Guide to the Danbury, Town of Records 1892-1969 DRG 1 DRG.1
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Danbury (Town of) Records
1892-1969
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
City of Danbury, Conn.
DRG.1
107
25.25 Linear Feet, 31 boxes
This is a small collection of the records of the Town of Danbury. It includes Selectmen, financial, School Board, Town Clerk, and Town Counsel records. Materials document town construction projects, social welfare, roads, the School Board, the airport, the 1955 Danbury flood, the agreement between the town and the AFSCME/AFL-CIO, the 1934 project for sewers, drains and treatment plant, town audits, town taxes and 1950s fallout shelters. These documents include announcements of upcoming Town Meetings, school bonds, budgets, property transactions, petitions, tax revaluation and appeals, town financial statements and a ledger of Registered Physicians in Danbury.
Provenance
These materials were recovered in the late 1970s by faculty of WestConn and donated to the Archives.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Danbury was served by a town government led by selectmen and a city government led by a mayor after receiving a city charter in 1889. This duality existed until the 1960s when the government was consolidated.
A Board of Selectmen is a construct implemented in New England area town governments to aid in execution of executive authority. The board may consist of three or five members of varying terms. Of that number, the First Selectman is the senior member of the board and the role of that First Selectman is akin to a town manager in other areas of the United States. The First Selectman was the chief elected official and administrative head of the town of Danbury. The correspondence generated by this office concerns a range of municipal government activities such as: maintaining municipal facilities, budget and financial issues, schools and education, town meetings, traffic planning and control, street closures and road work, civil defense, bids and contracts with local and state contractors, tax reports and tax relief, and public welfare issues. The files also contain maps and blueprints of various building projects and roadwork.
Justice of the Peace Aaron T. Bates was the son of Taylor Bates and was born in Ridgefield, CT in 1846. He studied law with Danbury's White & McDonald firm and was admitted to the Bar in 1874. He was married and had 2 children as of 1896.
Scope and Content Note
Series I Financial Records contains audit reports for the town, budgets, and various financial reports regarding prospective expenditures.
Series II: School Board contains ledgers accounting for School Board expenditures and the Board's meeting minutes.
Series III: Town Clerk contains various records primarily from the 1930s. This series remains partially unprocessed and also contains "old age" vouchers and miscellany.
Series IV: Town Counsel
The collection spans from 1893 to 1963 with the bulk of the collection ranging from 1940-1962, and is arranged chronologically by year or in groups of years. Most of the 1950s and forward correspondence is to Charles A. Hallock (Judge Hallock), the Town Council and Board of Selectmen. James A. Hallock was an attorney in Danbury who lived at 6 Pleasant St.
Of particular interest are the purchase of land for the development of Danbury Airport (box 9, folders 12-13, 21-25, 62-63), and the proposed Algonquin Gas pipeline through Danbury (box 1, folders 46-50).
Researchers should also see the Truman Warner Collection, a) Energy and Evolution, b) Air Travel, and c) Area Schools; the June Goodman Collection regarding education issues in Danbury; and, the City and Town of Danbury Records--Selectman Correspondence files for additional information concerning the development of Danbury Airport, Algonquin Gas Transmission Company, and school building and bonding issues.
The Algonquin Gas Transmission Company files contain correspondence, which includes the controversy surrounding their proposal, and maps indicating the proposed crossings of their pipeline through the Town of Danbury. The crossings include Saw Mill Road, Ridgebury Road, Driftway Road, Westville Avenue & Filmore Road, Franklin Street, Kohanza Street, Overlook Terrace, Terrace Road, Hayestown Road, Circle Drive, Great Plain Road, Rock Well Road, Hady Lane, Proposed Right Of Way for Pipeline Across the Property of Town of Danbury, East Hayestown Road, Oak Lane, and East Pembrook Road.
These records also contain correspondence and legal papers concerning the conveyance, by the State of Connecticut to the Town of Danbury, of a portion of the land on Roberts Avenue that was to be used to construct a laboratory school for the students of Danbury Teachers College (box 9, folders 33-36, 40-41, and blueprint of site OS 1).
This series was first described as the Town/City of Danbury Legal Papers; however, the name of the collection was modified to encompass the fact that most documents involve the Town Counsel, Danbury Board of Selectmen and the Danbury Town Council.
Series V: Registered Physicians contains a list of physicians in the Danbury area.
Series VI: Selectmen, Board of 1914-1960/DG179 and DG 209
This is a small collection of the Town of Danbury Selectmen records. The first series is comprised of correspondence directed to the First Selectman. In the years encompassed by this series, those selectmen were: Joeseph E. Sauer, Marquis Schlitter, and Charles Sweeney. Materials document the 1955 Danbury flood, the agreement between Town and AFSCME/AFL-CIO, 1934 project for sewers, drains and a treatment plant, and 1950s fallout shelters.
The second subseries contains files concerning the development of Danbury Airport (box 13, folders 4-9; box 14, folders 73-78, 82-91; box 7. folder 332; and oversized drawer 8; and, the proposed Algonquin Gas Line (box 13, folder 12, box 3, folder 177). Researchers should also see the Town and City of Danbury-Legal Papers Collection for additional information on the Danbury Airport and Algonquin Gas Transmission Company.
Information concerning Danbury during WW II can be found in the following folders: Box 13, folders 1-3, 53; box 14, folder 70a, 93-94, 97; box 16, folder 185-186, 214-215; box 17, folder 291; and box 19, folders 315-323, and 331-332). Additional information concerning the Danbury Airport, Algonquin Gas Line Transmission Company, and World War II are scattered among the alphabetical miscellaneous files.
Dating back to the colonial era, Danbury assumed responsibility, to varying degrees for its citizens who were destitute, sick, homeless, or otherwise unable to care for themselves. The files concerning the operation of Broadview Farm, the town's almshouse, between 1869-1962 can be found in Box 13, folders 14-15, 22-23, 46-47, 50-51, and 55-58. Researchers should also see Broadview Farm, 1869-1962 by Gladys B. Hammond, located in the Truman Warner Collection, Student Theses #31, which contains photographs and blueprints of the farm.
Series VII: Justice Docket (Aaron Bates)
The series is comprised of ledgers listing cases presumably overseen by Aaron T. Bates and civil cases held in the Danbury court house (in which Bates is listed as an attorney appearing before the court). Names, nature of charges and costs are indicated but the disposition of the case is not always noted.
Related Material
Danbury Ledgers
Danbury, City of Records
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 6 series:
Series I: Financial Records
Series II: School Board
Series III: Town Clerk
Series IV: Town Counsel
Series V: Registered Physicians, 1893-1937
Series VI: Selectmen, Board of 1914-1960
Series VII: Justice Docket
Veterans -- Services for -- United States.; Reports.; Danbury (Conn.); Public welfare -- Connecticut.; Ordinances, Municipal -- Connecticut -- Danbury.; Laboratory Schools.; Building permits.; Blueprints (reprographic copies).; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Minutes.; Maps.; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Fliers (printed matter); Dockets.; Ledgers (account books).; Algonquin Gas Transmission Company.; Brainard Field, Hartford.; Almshouse-Connecticut-Danbury.; Burkett, William A.; Citizens Food & Fuel Conservation Program.; Civil Air Patrol.; Conn-Air, Inc.; Connecticut Department of Transportation.; Connecticut. Commissioner on Domestic Animals.; Continental, Inc.; Danbury & Bethel Gas Electric Light Company.; Danbury Airport.; Danbury Aviation Commission.; Danbury School of Aeronautics, Inc.; Danbury State College Laboratory School.; Danbury Veterans Housing Units.; Danbury, Conn. Board of Selectmen.; Eagle Pencil Company.; Dyer Sales & Machinery Company.; Dolan Contracting Company.; Danbury, Conn. Town Clerks Office.; Hadfield, Rothwell, Soule & Coates.; Food Conservation Program.; Federal Works Agency.; F. A. Bartlett Tree Expert Company.; Park Avenue School.; Miry Brook Volunteer Fire Company, Inc.; Hayestown School.; Hallock, Charles A.; Sun Oil Company.; Serre, Joseph A.; Bates, Aaron T.; Serre, John C.; Roberts Avenue School.; The Texas Company.; Veteran's Home Commission (Rocky Hill, Conn.); The American Oil Company.; The American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME).; Works Progress Administration.; Veterans' Home and Hospital (Rocky Hill, Conn.); Wenzick, Roy & Company.
- Series I: Financial Records, 27317
  - Audit Reports, 27431
    - Report on the estimated cash receipts and disbursements for the fiscal year., 1923; 27474 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Supplementary report regarding financial records and mode for keeping them, 1924; 27473 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Exhibits and schedules covering the transactions for the year ended Sep 15, 1924, 27472 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Report covering schedules and tables fro supporting the recommendation as to the rate of tax covering the fiscal year ending Sep 15, 1924, 27471 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Report covering schedules and tables fro supporting the recommendation as to the rate of tax covering the fiscal year ending Sep 15, 1925, 27470 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Report on Town of Danbury Status of Town Tax Collector, 1934; 27469 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report on Town of Danbury (w/ handwritten insert), 1934; 27468 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Report on Town of Danbury, 1934; 27467 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Haskins & Sells Correspondence, 1935; 27466 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Audit Report, 1935; 27465 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Report on Examination of Accounts for the fiscal year, 1935; 27464 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Report on Examination of Accounts for the fiscal year, 1935; 27463 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Report on examination of recorded cash receipts and expenditures for the three months ended Dec 31, 1935, 27462 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Report on examination of recorded cash receipts and expenditures for the three months ended, March 31, 1936, 27461 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Report on Examination of Accounts for the fiscal year, 1936; 27460 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1936; 27459 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1936; 27458 (Box 2, Item 2)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1937; 27457 (Box 2, Item 3)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1938; 27456 (Box 2, Item 4)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1939; 27455 (Box 2, Item 5)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1939; 27454 (Box 2, Item 6)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1940; 27453 (Box 2, Item 7)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1941; 27452 (Box 2, Item 8)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1942; 27451 (Box 2, Item 9)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1943; 27450 (Box 2, Item 10)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1944; 27449 (Box 2, Item 11)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1944; 27448 (Box 2, Item 12)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1944; 27447 (Box 2, Item 13)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1945; 27446 (Box 2, Item 14)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1945; 27445 (Box 2, Item 15)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1945; 27444 (Box 2, Item 16)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1945; 27443 (Box 2, Item 17)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Work Papers, 1945; 27442 (Box 2, Item 18)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1946; 27441 (Box 2, Item 19)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1947; 27440 (Box 2, Item 20)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1948; 27439 (Box 2, Item 21)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1950; 27438 (Box 2, Item 22)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1951; 27437 (Box 2, Item 23)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1955; 27436 (Box 2, Item 24)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1956; 27435 (Box 2, Item 25)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1957; 27434 (Box 2, Item 26)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1958; 27433 (Box 2, Item 27)
    - Office of Tax Collector, Auditors Report, 1961; 27432 (Box 2, Item 28)
  - Budgets 1949-1970 (Bulk 1949-1960)/ Acc #177-1976, 27417
    - Town Budget, 1949-1950; 27430 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      General note
      Appropriations between 7/1/49 to 3/31/50 which include general government expenses, highways and bridges, charities, social services, education, and insurance schedules.
    - Town Budget, 1950-1951; 27429 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Agreement for town audit, town budget, school budget, monthly budget reports, and appropriations.
    - Town Budget, 1951-1952; 27428 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Board of Finance minutes, Town Grand List dated 10/1/50-1951, Town Collectors Budget, Town and school bonds, monthly budget reports, appropriations, tentative budget of the Town Recreation Commission.
    - Town Budget, 1952-1953; 27427 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      School budget, monthly budget reports, appropriations, Board of Education appropriations and expenditures, Town Recreation Commission, Danbury War Memorial Association, and Board of Finance minutes.
    - Town Budget, 1953-1954; 27426 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Office of Civil Defense War Memorial, Tax Collector, town Recreation Commission, Danbury Library, Assessor's office, Danbury War Memorial Association, monthly budget reports, minutes from the Special Meetings of the Board of Finance, and school budget.
    - Town Budget, 1954-1955; 27425 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Monthly budget reports, Tax Collector, Danbury War Memorial Association, Tax Collector, Assessor's office, appropriations, Danbury Library, tentative budget of the Town Recreation Commission, and school budget.
    - Town Budget, 1955-1956; 27424 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
      Correspondence, monthly budget reports, appropriations, school budgets, Civil Defense, teachers' salaries, Town Recreation Commission, Tax Collector, and budget minutes.
    - Town Budget, 1956-1957; 27423 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
      Correspondence, monthly budget reports, Board of Finance minutes, school estimates, Grand List, Danbury War Memorial Association, Civil Defense, Danbury Library,
    - Town Budget, 1957-1958; 27422 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      School estimates, appropriations, Board of Finance, War Memorial, Assessor's office, Tax Collector, school bonds, Danbury Library, and correspondence.
    - Town Budget, 1959-1960; 27421 (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
      Monthly budget reports, correspondence, appropriations, estimated tax rate, Grand List as of October 1, 1958, Civil Defense, Tax Collector, town bonds, Danbury War Memorial Association, tentative budget of the Town Recreation Commission, Danbury Library, school estimates, and re-evaluation of properties for Grand List.
    - Town Budget, 1967-1968; 27420 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Published budget for the City of Danbury that includes the General Fund, Budget, Dog Fund Budget, and Water Fund Budget.
    - Town Budget, 1968-1969; 27419 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Published budget for the City of Danbury that includes the General Fund Budget, Dog Fund Budget, and the Water Fund Budget.
    - Capital Expenditures Program, March 1970, 27418 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Published Report by Technical Planning Associates, Consultants.
  - Financial Reports, 1923-1959 (w/gaps)/Acc #178-1976, 27397
    - The Real Estate Analyst, 1953; 27416 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      A proposal to revalue all taxable and tax exempt real property by Roy Wenzick & Company dated April 21, 1953.
    - Danbury Airport, 1935-1959; 27415 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Proposal for the airport by the Chamber of Commerce; Danbury Airport Corporation financial report dated October 31, 1935; airport contract regarding proposed airport development dated July 1, 1959; grant agreement; map of the Municipal Airport - Project Document #9-06-011-03.
    - Danbury Airport, 1957; 27414 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
      Aerial photographs (18) and a report entitled Danbury Airport published by the Danbury Chamber of Commerce, June 1957.
    - Unsuccessful Bidders, 1962; 27413 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Restoration work on City Hall.
    - Eagle Pencil Company, 1958; 27412 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      A bid from the E. Paul Kovacs & Company, Inc. for the proposed highway construction to Eagle Pencil Company.
    - Town Report, 1937; 27411 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Report of activities of town government during fiscal year ending June 30, 1937.
    - Danbury Housing Authority, 1948; 27410 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Veterans Housing Authority Rules and Regulations, minutes of meetings, and correspondence with Connecticut State Housing Authority.
    - Veterans Applications for Housing, 1948; 27409 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Power Lines and Pipelines, 1951-1955; 27408 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
      Lawsuit between Town of Danbury and Algonquin Gas Transmission Company. Danbury charged AGT of trespassing through Northern Danbury. Includes rules and regulations and construction standards for high-pressure gas transmission.
    - Unsuccessful Bidders, 1958; 27407 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Correspondence between engineers and various contracting firms for proposed highway construction to Eagle Pencil Company.
    - Bridge Reports, undated; 27406 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Sketches and surveys of town bridges noting conditions and recommendations for repair.
    - Danbury Housing Authority (Accepted), 1948; 27405 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
      Applications for housing.
    - Planning Commission, 1967; 27404 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
      Minutes of meetings regarding zoning regulations for personal and public property.
    - Planning Commission, 1968; 27403 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - Planning Commission, 1969; 27402 (Box 5, Folder 20-21)
    - Planning Commission, 1970; 27401 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
      Minutes of meetings regarding zoning regulations for personal and public property. January-July 1970.
    - Sinking Fund Report, 1932; 27400 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      Analysis and summary of Sinking Fund investments by Hadfield, Rothwell, Soule & Coates.
    - Taxable Real Estate, 1933; 27399 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
      Lists of taxable real estate, Board of Relief Changes, for the Town and City of Danbury.
    - Tax Foreclosed Property, Call for bids on, 1958; 27398 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Annual Reports, 1893-1964/Acc #191-1976, 27322
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1893; 27396 (Box 5.1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1894; 27395 (Box 5.1, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1895; 27394 (Box 5.1, Folder 3)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1896; 27393 (Box 5.1, Folder 4)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1897; 27392 (Box 5.1, Folder 5)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1898; 27391 (Box 5.1, Folder 6)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1899; 27390 (Box 5.1, Folder 7)
    - Report of The Special Committee on Expense of Town Poor, 1899; 27389 (Box 5.1, Folder 8)
    - Annual Report of the Board of School Visitors and the Joint Board of Selectmen And School Visitors of the Town of Danbury, 1899; 27388 (Box 5.1, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1900; 27387 (Box 5.1, Folder 10)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1901; 27386 (Box 5.1, Folder 11)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1902; 27385 (Box 5.1, Folder 12)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1904; 27384 (Box 5.1, Folder 13)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1905; 27383 (Box 5.1, Folder 14)
    - Annual Report. Selectmen, Year ending Sept. 15, 1907, and Annual Report Secretary Town School Committee, Year Ending Sept. 15, 1907., 27382 (Box 5.1, Folder 15)
    - Annual Report. Selectmen Year ending Sept. 15, 1908, and Annual Report Town School Committee, Year ending Sept. 15, 1908., 27381 (Box 5.1, Folder 16)
    - Annual Report. Selectmen Town of Danbury, Conn., Year Ending Sept. 15, 1909, and Annual Report. Town School Committee, Superintendent of Schools, Year Ending Sept. 15, 1909., 27380 (Box 5.1, Folder 17)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1911; 27379 (Box 5.1, Folder 18)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1914; 27378 (Box 5.1, Folder 19)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1916; 27377 (Box 5.1, Folder 20)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1917; 27376 (Box 5.1, Folder 21)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1918; 27375 (Box 5.1, Folder 22)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1919; 27374 (Box 5.1, Folder 23)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1920; 27373 (Box 5.1, Folder 24)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1921; 27372 (Box 5.1, Folder 25)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1922; 27371 (Box 5.1, Folder 26)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1923; 27370 (Box 5.1, Folder 27)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1924; 27369 (Box 5.1, Folder 28)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1925; 27368 (Box 5.1, Folder 29)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1926; 27367 (Box 5.1, Folder 30)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1927; 27366 (Box 5.1, Folder 31)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1928; 27365 (Box 5.1, Folder 32)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1929; 27364 (Box 5.1, Folder 33)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1930; 27363 (Box 5.1, Folder 34)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1931; 27362 (Box 5.1, Folder 35)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1932; 27361 (Box 5.1, Folder 36)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1933; 27360 (Box 5.1, Folder 37)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1935; 27359 (Box 5.1, Folder 38)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1936; 27358 (Box 5.1, Folder 39)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1937; 27357 (Box 5.1, Folder 40)
    - Annual Report of the Board of Selectmen of the Town of Danbury, 1938; 27356 (Box 5.1, Folder 41)